<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Writing | William John Bert]]></title>
  <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/categories/writing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-04T22:33:05-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[William John Bert]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Poetry for the President]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/05/poetry-for-the-president/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-11T07:43:10-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/05/poetry-for-the-president</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/IMG_1361-1.jpg"><img src="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/IMG_1361-1.jpg" alt="" /></a>Since March, I've been working with DC students from several high schools, including Duke Ellington, Ballou, Wilson and Bell, in evening poetry workshops at <a href="http://www.826dc.org">826DC</a>. A bunch of us have been helping out—Mike Scalise, Adam Pelligrini, and Sally Keith (the last two being actual poets, while Mike and I, both prose writers, were faking it the whole time). And of course program director Mariam Al-Shawaf and 826DC Executive Director Joe Callahan did the thankless behind-the-scenes labor to make it all happen.</p>

<p>The students came to us talented and hard-working, and we just helped them along with workshops on poetic forms, poetic sound, and metaphor (this is the one I'm awkwardly teaching in the photo above), and by giving plenty of exercises and time to generate new material. We even had a guest visit from the amazing <a href="http://www.poetryfoundation.org/bio/carolyn-forche">Carolyn Forche</a>.</p>

<p>All this <a href="http://english.georgetown.edu/217153.html">culminates today</a> in a <a href="http://www.826national.org/article/405/826dc-and-826chi-students-write-poetry-at-the-white-house">workshop at the White House</a>, hosted by the Obamas, where the students will work with the likes of Billy Collins, Common, Rita Dove, Aimee Mann, Jill Scott and several other amazing poets to hone their craft even further. Very, very cool. Congrats to 826DC and especially to the students!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring, spring, spring]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/05/spring-spring-spring/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-09T05:59:26-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/05/spring-spring-spring</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/jbb_cr2.jpg"><img src="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/jbb_cr2.jpg" alt="" /></a>Spring is the rarest of seasons in DC, but it looks like we get a few days of it this week. This could not be happening at a better time. The protracted move from Columbia Heights/Baltimore/Tucson to Capitol Hill is over. The <a href="http://www.callandresponsedc.org/">art show</a> has wrapped. Work is still way busy, but next week I head to North Carolina for some writing time in the mountains at <a href="http://doebranchink.org/">Doe Branch Ink</a>--the ideal vacation.</p>

<p>Craig Nova is the resident author for this session at DBI, and I'm looking forward to reading his novel <em>The Good Son</em>, starting on the commute home this afternoon. It'll be good to dive back into reading and writing, which have taken a back seat so far this season. I did have the honor of getting tapped for <a href="http://dcarts.dc.gov/DC/DCARTS/Events/Annual+Programming/Annual+Programming#4">a Larry Neal award</a>, 2nd place for adult fiction  (the non-euphemistic kind), for a story I began back in Arizona but kept revisiting up until last fall. That just made me want to sit down and get back to writing, drafting, and revising even more! I don't have any illusions that late spring and summer will be slow, but few things suck up time more than moving, and with a good solid week to get jump-started, I'm feeling optimistic.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New story, and other updates]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/03/new-story-in-anomalous-press/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-23T07:35:36-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/03/new-story-in-anomalous-press</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/anomalous1.png"><img src="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/anomalous1.png" alt="Anomalous Press #1" /></a>I'm really thrilled to have a story, <a href="http://www.anomalouspress.org/current/21.bert.winner.php">"Winner,"</a> in the very first issue of Anomalous Press. It was released on the Ides of March, so I'm a bit tardy announcing it here—it's been a busy March so far.</p>

<p>The issue includes work from many better writers than me, including <a href="http://www.anomalouspress.org/current/25.ayala.winter.php">a poem</a> and <a href="http://www.anomalouspress.org/current/26.ayala.vision.php">two translations</a> from my friend Naomi Ayala. It was Naomi who suggested I submit to Anomalous. In this way and many others, she's been a great friend and supporter of my writing, and I hope someday to be able to pay her back. You can catch another poem of hers when <a href="http://www.callandresponsedc.org/">Call + Response: Textures</a> opens on April 16. (More on that tomorrow.)</p>

<p>Anomalous Press #1 is available for download as a PDF, but only if you <a href="http://www.paywithatweet.com/">pay with a tweet</a>. Neat concept. Attention as currency. And from a technical standpoint, I'm interested in how they integrated with <a href="http://dev.twitter.com/">Twitter using OAuth</a>—I want to do a similar thing with the reading series web app (Readsr/Readthing/whatever) I'm working on: tweet whenever a reading series is updated. So I'll be looking into this soon.</p>

<p>First, though, I plan to deploy an alpha version of the site this weekend. I've been reading up on <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/virtualenv">virtualenv</a>, <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/pip">pip</a>, <a href="http://fabfile.org/">fabric</a>, and <a href="http://git-scm.com/">git</a>, trying to figure out how to deploy the right way--with automated version control and dependency isolation. This part, the admin stuff, is as complicated as any coding problem I've faced. Looking forward to tackling it in a marathon session on Saturday!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stuff: Happening]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/02/stuff-happening/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-22T15:06:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/02/stuff-happening</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/IMG_0746.jpg"><img src="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/IMG_0746.jpg" alt="Plane flying in clouds" /></a>If I updated more regularly, I would have written entire posts about the following things.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>AWP 2011 came and went blazingly fast. I saw many people I've missed dearly, and missed many people I would've liked to see.</p></li>
<li><p>The second workshop with the Bell Poetry Club for <a href="http://www.826dc.org/">826DC</a>, this time diving into the poem-as-extended-metaphor, went swimmingly.</p></li>
<li><p>A story of mine is going to be published in the first issue of Anomalous.</p></li>
<li><p>And I continue working on my reading series Django app. Possible names: Readsr, or Readzee, or Readoo, or maybe Readthing. Hmm. Are any of these, like, any good? Tonight's task: refactoring and adding messaging.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bell Poetry Club]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/01/bell-poetry-club/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-30T10:11:27-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/01/bell-poetry-club</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/IMG_0758.jpg"><img src="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/IMG_0758.jpg" alt="Potomac River ice" /></a></p>

<p>Friday, I helped out with an 826DC workshop at Bell Multicultural High School in Columbia Heights. Bell's Poetry Club meets after school each Friday, and we came by  to work with them on metaphor. To fuel the discussion, we read "Snow Leopards at the Denver Zoo" by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Matthews_%28poet%29">William Matthews</a> (who I'd never heard of before—I'm so not a poet):</p>

<blockquote><pre><code>There are only a hundred or so
snow leopards alive, and three
of them here. Hours I watch them jump
down and jump up, water being
poured. Though if you fill a glass
fast with water, it rings high to the top,
noise of a nail driven true. Snow
leopards land without sound,
as if they were already extinct.





If I could, I’d sift them
from hand to hand, like a fire,
like a debt I can count but can’t pay.
I’m glad I can’t. If I tried to
take loss for a wife, and I do,
and keep her all the days of my life,
I’d have nothing to leave my children.
I save them whatever I can keep
and I pour it from hand to hand.
</code></pre></blockquote>

<p>A few metaphors there, huh? It's a swift poem, turning from accessible to knotty in the space of a few lines. Great for discussion, and the students were more than up to the task. The writing exercise we did next further showed off their chops. We all took 20 minutes to write a poem full of metaphors, then shared them with the group. Their stuff leapt off the page, lyrical, narrative, associative, wild and subtle and everything between.</p>

<p>All of us from 826DC  were seriously impressed, and I look forward to hanging out with the Bell Poetry Club again in a couple weeks. It's on us to come up with something new to challenge these talents—my prediction is we're going to learn just as much as they do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
