<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Teaching | William John Bert]]></title>
  <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/categories/teaching/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-02T15:12:17-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[William John Bert]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Novelties & Traditions]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/11/novelties-traditions/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-19T05:28:21-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/11/novelties-traditions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today's the third annual Friendsgiving, a Thanksgiving-like pre-Thanksgiving event for a bunch of people who like each other; hence, Friendsgiving. Thanksgiving's always been my favorite holiday so I'm more than happy to celebrate it twice a year. The first two Friendsgivings took place at my house, but because in the spring I traded my room in a cavernous and amply chandeliered group rowhouse for cozier and warmer digs, the honor of hosting this year falls to two friends who're renting an entire lovely house for themselves up in Pleasant Plains. Sweet.</p>

<p>So much for traditions; recent novelties include starting a new job, about which more another time, but basically, I love it; and getting a lesson plan published in <a href="http://www.amzn.com/111802432X">Don't Forget to Write</a>, the second volume of lesson plans from <a href="http://www.826national.org/">826</a>. The lesson plan, "Busted," aims to make storytellers out of middle schoolers by having them write about a time they got caught doing something they shouldn't have been doing--a theme first cooked up by the folks who led the <a href="http://826dc.org/?p=510">Get Used to the Seats</a> book project. I <a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2010/11/caught-in-the-act-part-3/">wrote about leading the workshops that ultimately became the "Busted" lesson plan</a> more than a year ago--right around the previous Friendsgiving. Hard to believe it's been that long!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Poetry for the President]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/05/poetry-for-the-president/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-11T07:43:10-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/05/poetry-for-the-president</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/IMG_1361-1.jpg"><img src="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/IMG_1361-1.jpg" alt="" /></a>Since March, I've been working with DC students from several high schools, including Duke Ellington, Ballou, Wilson and Bell, in evening poetry workshops at <a href="http://www.826dc.org">826DC</a>. A bunch of us have been helping out—Mike Scalise, Adam Pelligrini, and Sally Keith (the last two being actual poets, while Mike and I, both prose writers, were faking it the whole time). And of course program director Mariam Al-Shawaf and 826DC Executive Director Joe Callahan did the thankless behind-the-scenes labor to make it all happen.</p>

<p>The students came to us talented and hard-working, and we just helped them along with workshops on poetic forms, poetic sound, and metaphor (this is the one I'm awkwardly teaching in the photo above), and by giving plenty of exercises and time to generate new material. We even had a guest visit from the amazing <a href="http://www.poetryfoundation.org/bio/carolyn-forche">Carolyn Forche</a>.</p>

<p>All this <a href="http://english.georgetown.edu/217153.html">culminates today</a> in a <a href="http://www.826national.org/article/405/826dc-and-826chi-students-write-poetry-at-the-white-house">workshop at the White House</a>, hosted by the Obamas, where the students will work with the likes of Billy Collins, Common, Rita Dove, Aimee Mann, Jill Scott and several other amazing poets to hone their craft even further. Very, very cool. Congrats to 826DC and especially to the students!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stuff: Happening]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/02/stuff-happening/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-22T15:06:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/02/stuff-happening</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/IMG_0746.jpg"><img src="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/IMG_0746.jpg" alt="Plane flying in clouds" /></a>If I updated more regularly, I would have written entire posts about the following things.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>AWP 2011 came and went blazingly fast. I saw many people I've missed dearly, and missed many people I would've liked to see.</p></li>
<li><p>The second workshop with the Bell Poetry Club for <a href="http://www.826dc.org/">826DC</a>, this time diving into the poem-as-extended-metaphor, went swimmingly.</p></li>
<li><p>A story of mine is going to be published in the first issue of Anomalous.</p></li>
<li><p>And I continue working on my reading series Django app. Possible names: Readsr, or Readzee, or Readoo, or maybe Readthing. Hmm. Are any of these, like, any good? Tonight's task: refactoring and adding messaging.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bell Poetry Club]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/01/bell-poetry-club/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-30T10:11:27-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/01/bell-poetry-club</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/IMG_0758.jpg"><img src="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/IMG_0758.jpg" alt="Potomac River ice" /></a></p>

<p>Friday, I helped out with an 826DC workshop at Bell Multicultural High School in Columbia Heights. Bell's Poetry Club meets after school each Friday, and we came by  to work with them on metaphor. To fuel the discussion, we read "Snow Leopards at the Denver Zoo" by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Matthews_%28poet%29">William Matthews</a> (who I'd never heard of before—I'm so not a poet):</p>

<blockquote><pre><code>There are only a hundred or so
snow leopards alive, and three
of them here. Hours I watch them jump
down and jump up, water being
poured. Though if you fill a glass
fast with water, it rings high to the top,
noise of a nail driven true. Snow
leopards land without sound,
as if they were already extinct.





If I could, I’d sift them
from hand to hand, like a fire,
like a debt I can count but can’t pay.
I’m glad I can’t. If I tried to
take loss for a wife, and I do,
and keep her all the days of my life,
I’d have nothing to leave my children.
I save them whatever I can keep
and I pour it from hand to hand.
</code></pre></blockquote>

<p>A few metaphors there, huh? It's a swift poem, turning from accessible to knotty in the space of a few lines. Great for discussion, and the students were more than up to the task. The writing exercise we did next further showed off their chops. We all took 20 minutes to write a poem full of metaphors, then shared them with the group. Their stuff leapt off the page, lyrical, narrative, associative, wild and subtle and everything between.</p>

<p>All of us from 826DC  were seriously impressed, and I look forward to hanging out with the Bell Poetry Club again in a couple weeks. It's on us to come up with something new to challenge these talents—my prediction is we're going to learn just as much as they do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Caught in the Act, Part 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2010/11/caught-in-the-act-part-3/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-26T06:23:23-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2010/11/caught-in-the-act-part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/IMG_0640.jpg"><img src="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/IMG_0640.jpg" alt="Sign for Caught in the Act workshop in 826DC window" /></a>Tuesday night was the final workshop of the <a href="../2010/11/teaching-a-workshop-tonight/">three</a>-<a href="../2010/11/caught-in-the-act-part-2/">part</a> Caught in the Act series that I've been leading at <a href="http://www.826dc.org/">826DC</a>. I played trombone in high school band, and I remember the teacher telling us that the most challenging pieces weren't the flashy <em>allegro fortissimo</em> showpieces (however much we enjoyed them) but rather the <em>lento piano</em> passages--unassuming, soft and slow, but deceptively difficult because they exposed your playing to a high level of scrutiny and vulnerability.</p>

<p>I think something similar applies to large vs. small workshops. When students far outnumber TAs, your work is cut out for you: keep circulating, keep the students on task, give as much attention to each as you can, and try to get through the whole class plan in the allotted time.</p>

<p>Teaching a very small workshop presented its own set of challenges: with everyone getting one-on-one attention, I worried the students would feel on display, over-attended-to, and uncomfortable, like patrons in an empty restaurant.</p>

<p>What I tried to do was have us all be in it together: we all sat at the same table, all did each of the exercises, and all read everyone else's work. Did it work? I think so; the students kept coming back, anyway. And I was really impressed with the stories everyone ended up with. Truth is, I was lucky to have such a great group--students and TAs--to work with; they deserve pretty much all the credit!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
