<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Publications | William John Bert]]></title>
  <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/categories/publications/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-02T10:39:12-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[William John Bert]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Novelties & Traditions]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/11/novelties-traditions/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-19T05:28:21-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/11/novelties-traditions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today's the third annual Friendsgiving, a Thanksgiving-like pre-Thanksgiving event for a bunch of people who like each other; hence, Friendsgiving. Thanksgiving's always been my favorite holiday so I'm more than happy to celebrate it twice a year. The first two Friendsgivings took place at my house, but because in the spring I traded my room in a cavernous and amply chandeliered group rowhouse for cozier and warmer digs, the honor of hosting this year falls to two friends who're renting an entire lovely house for themselves up in Pleasant Plains. Sweet.</p>

<p>So much for traditions; recent novelties include starting a new job, about which more another time, but basically, I love it; and getting a lesson plan published in <a href="http://www.amzn.com/111802432X">Don't Forget to Write</a>, the second volume of lesson plans from <a href="http://www.826national.org/">826</a>. The lesson plan, "Busted," aims to make storytellers out of middle schoolers by having them write about a time they got caught doing something they shouldn't have been doing--a theme first cooked up by the folks who led the <a href="http://826dc.org/?p=510">Get Used to the Seats</a> book project. I <a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2010/11/caught-in-the-act-part-3/">wrote about leading the workshops that ultimately became the "Busted" lesson plan</a> more than a year ago--right around the previous Friendsgiving. Hard to believe it's been that long!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New story, and other updates]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/03/new-story-in-anomalous-press/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-23T07:35:36-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/03/new-story-in-anomalous-press</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/anomalous1.png"><img src="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/anomalous1.png" alt="Anomalous Press #1" /></a>I'm really thrilled to have a story, <a href="http://www.anomalouspress.org/current/21.bert.winner.php">"Winner,"</a> in the very first issue of Anomalous Press. It was released on the Ides of March, so I'm a bit tardy announcing it here—it's been a busy March so far.</p>

<p>The issue includes work from many better writers than me, including <a href="http://www.anomalouspress.org/current/25.ayala.winter.php">a poem</a> and <a href="http://www.anomalouspress.org/current/26.ayala.vision.php">two translations</a> from my friend Naomi Ayala. It was Naomi who suggested I submit to Anomalous. In this way and many others, she's been a great friend and supporter of my writing, and I hope someday to be able to pay her back. You can catch another poem of hers when <a href="http://www.callandresponsedc.org/">Call + Response: Textures</a> opens on April 16. (More on that tomorrow.)</p>

<p>Anomalous Press #1 is available for download as a PDF, but only if you <a href="http://www.paywithatweet.com/">pay with a tweet</a>. Neat concept. Attention as currency. And from a technical standpoint, I'm interested in how they integrated with <a href="http://dev.twitter.com/">Twitter using OAuth</a>—I want to do a similar thing with the reading series web app (Readsr/Readthing/whatever) I'm working on: tweet whenever a reading series is updated. So I'll be looking into this soon.</p>

<p>First, though, I plan to deploy an alpha version of the site this weekend. I've been reading up on <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/virtualenv">virtualenv</a>, <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/pip">pip</a>, <a href="http://fabfile.org/">fabric</a>, and <a href="http://git-scm.com/">git</a>, trying to figure out how to deploy the right way--with automated version control and dependency isolation. This part, the admin stuff, is as complicated as any coding problem I've faced. Looking forward to tackling it in a marathon session on Saturday!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stuff: Happening]]></title>
    <link href="http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/02/stuff-happening/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-22T15:06:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://williamjohnbert.com/2011/02/stuff-happening</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/IMG_0746.jpg"><img src="http://williamjohnbert.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/IMG_0746.jpg" alt="Plane flying in clouds" /></a>If I updated more regularly, I would have written entire posts about the following things.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>AWP 2011 came and went blazingly fast. I saw many people I've missed dearly, and missed many people I would've liked to see.</p></li>
<li><p>The second workshop with the Bell Poetry Club for <a href="http://www.826dc.org/">826DC</a>, this time diving into the poem-as-extended-metaphor, went swimmingly.</p></li>
<li><p>A story of mine is going to be published in the first issue of Anomalous.</p></li>
<li><p>And I continue working on my reading series Django app. Possible names: Readsr, or Readzee, or Readoo, or maybe Readthing. Hmm. Are any of these, like, any good? Tonight's task: refactoring and adding messaging.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
